<!-- <?xml version='1.0'?> -->

<!--

IF YOU CAN READ THIS, YOUR BROWSER DOESN'T SUPPORT XML.

PLEASE UPDATE YOUR BROWSER, OR VIEW THE HTML VERSION OF THIS PAGE.

-->
<!--
When the schema works, reference it like this; change the project tag below to this
<project xmlns:xsi = "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation = "isd-personnel.xsd">
-->
<project>
  <name>EMeD</name>
  <title>EXPECT Method Developer</title>

  <status>
    <short>
 The project has ended.
  </short>
  <long> Successful approaches to developing knowledge acquisition tools use
expectations of what the user has to add or may want to add, based on how new
knowledge fits within a knowledge base that already exists. When a knowledge
base is first created or undergoes significant extensions and changes, these
tools cannot provide much support. We present an approach to creating
expectations when a new knowledge base is built, and describes a knowledge
acquisition tool that we implemented using this approach that supports users
in creating problem-solving knowledge.  As the knowledge base grows, the
knowledge acquisition tool derives more frequent and more reliable
expectations that result from enforcing constraints in the knowledge
representation system, looking for missing pieces of knowledge in the
knowledge base, and working out incrementally the inter-dependencies among the
different components of the knowledge base.  Our preliminary evaluations show
a thirty percent time savings during knowledge acquisition.  Moreover, by
providing tools to support the initial phases of knowledge base development
many mistakes are detected early on and even avoided altogether. We believe
that our approach contributes to improving the quality of the knowledge
acquisition process and of the resulting knowledge-based systems as well.
</long>
 
  </status>

  <description>
    <short>
    
    </short>

    <long>
Successful approaches to developing knowledge acquisition tools use
expectations of what the user has to add or may want to add, based on how new
knowledge fits within a knowledge base that already exists. When a knowledge
base is first created or undergoes significant extensions and changes, these
tools cannot provide much support. We present an approach to creating
expectations when a new knowledge base is built, and describes a knowledge
acquisition tool that we implemented using this approach that supports users
in creating problem-solving knowledge.  As the knowledge base grows, the
knowledge acquisition tool derives more frequent and more reliable
expectations that result from enforcing constraints in the knowledge
representation system, looking for missing pieces of knowledge in the
knowledge base, and working out incrementally the inter-dependencies among the
different components of the knowledge base.  Our preliminary evaluations show
a thirty percent time savings during knowledge acquisition.  Moreover, by
providing tools to support the initial phases of knowledge base development
many mistakes are detected early on and even avoided altogether. We believe
that our approach contributes to improving the quality of the knowledge
acquisition process and of the resulting knowledge-based systems as well.
    </long>
  </description>

  <research>
    <short>
     Expectation, Acquiring Procedural Knowledge
    </short>
    <long>


We describe our approach to developing KA tools
that derive expectations from the KB in order to guide users
during KB creation. Through an analysis of the KB creation
task, we were able to detect several sources for such expectations.
The expectations result from enforcing constraints
in theknowledge representation system, lookingformissing
pieces of knowledge in the KB, and working out incrementally
the inter-dependencies among the different components
of the KB. As the user defines new KB elements (i.e.,
new concepts, new relations, new problem-solving knowledge),
the KA tool can form increasingly more frequent
and more reliable expectations. We implemented a KA
tool called EMeD that uses these sources of expectations to
support users in adding problem-solving knowledge. Our
preliminary evaluation shows an average time savings of
30% to enter the new knowledge. We believe it will be
even higher for users who are not experienced knowledge
engineers.

    </long>
  </research>

  <link>
  EMeD slides in various meetings
<ul>
  <li><a
href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/emed/slides/EMeD-poster.ppt">DARPA
High Performance Knowledge Bases program Workshop (January 1999)</a></li>
</ul>
  </link>



<!-- Demo -->
<demo>
<P>

</P>



     <center>
	  <img src="img1.jpg"/>
	  </center>


</demo>
</project>
