<!-- <?xml version='1.0'?> -->

<!--

IF YOU CAN READ THIS, YOUR BROWSER DOESN'T SUPPORT XML.

PLEASE UPDATE YOUR BROWSER, OR VIEW THE HTML VERSION OF THIS PAGE.

-->

<project>
<name>Calo</name>
<title>Learning through user instruction for personal assistants and agents</title>
<description>
<short>


<p> Calo (Cognitive assistant that learns and organizes) is a cognitive
personal assistant with a flexible plan execution system at its
heart. As part of the Calo project we are working to help users provide
advice to the plan execution system to customize its behavior to their
needs.
</p>

</short>
<long>
</long>
</description>
<status>
<short>

<p>We have developed the <a href="../tailor">Tailor</a> system to
demonstrate how providing advice can customize the behaviour of the plan
execution system in a deep way, modifying constraints and providing new
action definitions.</p>

</short>

<long>

<p>We have identified a set of interactions within a scenario where the
user is purchasing a laptop computer that demonstrate how providing
advice can customize the behaviour of the plan execution system in a
deep way, modifying constraints and providing new action
definitions.</p>

<p>For more details, see the <a href="../tailor">Tailor</a> project pages.</p>

<p>An initial set of sample interactions can be found 
<a href="interactions-9-19-03.txt">here</a>. They are intended for use
with Spark, a PRS-based plan execution system being developed as part of
Calo.
</p>

<p>We are working to implement some of these interactions and provide an
API to allow other modules within Calo to use the capabilities. We
welcome comments on the approach.</p>

</long>
</status>
<research>
<short>
Knowledge acquisition, advice for plan execution systems, KA scripts,
acquiring constraints. 
</short>
<long>

<p> Our work uses knowledge acquisition scripts, ontologies of
constraints, dialog and simple user interfaces, although that is not the
focus of our project. Some of our work is based on earlier projects such
as 
<a href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/temple">Temple</a> and 
<a href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/expect">Expect</a>.
</p>

<p> <a href="acquiring-advice.ppt">These powerpoint slides</a> discuss
some potential approaches to the project. Again, comments are most
welcome!
</p>

</long>
</research>

<link>
<a href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/echo"><b>The Echo project for memory-based
meta level reasoning and learning</b></a>
</link>

<link>
<a href="http://www.ai.sri.com/project/CALO"><b>SRI CALO project page (public access)</b></a>
</link>

<!-- Demo -->
<demo>
  <center>
<img src="tn_comingsoon.jpg"/>
</center>
</demo>
</project>

