<!-- <?xml version='1.0'?> -->

<!--

IF YOU CAN READ THIS, YOUR BROWSER DOESN'T SUPPORT XML.

PLEASE UPDATE YOUR BROWSER, OR VIEW THE HTML VERSION OF THIS PAGE.

-->
<!--
When the schema works, reference it like this; change the project tag below to this
<project xmlns:xsi = "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation = "isd-personnel.xsd">
-->
<project>
  <name>KANAL</name>
  <title>Knowledge Analysis on Process Models</title>

  <status>
    <short>
  KANAL is currently used within an end-to-end KA system called SHAKEN. We
have performed several evaluations with end users which are reported in <a 
href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/papers/kim-blythe-iui-2003.pdf">Kim and
Blythe, IUI-2003</a>.  

  </short>
  <long>
Our initial evaluation of <n /> as a stand-alone system shows its usefulness
in finding errors and suggesting fixes.  It also has been
successfully integrated within an end-to-end system that support users
entering domain knowledge as a part of DARPA Rapid Knowledge Formation (RKF)
program. 
<b><n /></b> is a tool for building and checking process models.  By
relating different pieces of information in process models among themselves
and to the existing KB, it performs a variety of verification and validation
checks and propose useful fixes.
  <p />

We performed an initial evaluation in December 2000, which has been reported in
<a 
href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/papers/kim-gil-ijcai01.pdf">Kim and
Gil, IJCAI-01</a>.  The results show that <n /> can find most of the errors in
the process models and suggest useful fixes including the fixes that directly
point to the sources of the errors.
<p />

<n /> has been successfully integrated within an end-to-end system (called
SHAKEN) that supports subject matter experts entering domain knowledge as part
of the DARPA <a href="http://reliant.teknowledge.com/RKF/">Rapid Knowledge
Formation (RKF)</a> program.  During summer 2001 and January 2002, the SHAKEN
system has been evaluated by lightly trained biologists where they author
biology textbook knowledge using the system.  The resulting knowledge bases 
answer questions that a student might be asked based on the
chapter's contents.  
<p />

We have recently built an Action Editor in order to support interleaving of process
model authoring and checking while extending background knowledge of actions.
Also we have refined the KANAL interface based on feedback from end users.
The improved system was evaluated by military officers in describing
and checking their plans (courses of actions) during Fall 2002. The details
are desribed in <a 
href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/papers/kim-blythe-iui-2003.pdf">Kim and
Blythe, IUI-2003</a>.

</long>
 
 </status>

  <description>
    <short>
     <n/> is a tool for checking process models entered by users.  By
relating different pieces of information in process models among themselves
and to the existing KB, it performs a variety of verification and validation
checks and propose useful fixes.  
    </short>

    <long>
<p />
<n/> relates pieces of information in process models among themselves
and to the existing KB, analyzing how different pieces of input are put
together to achieve some effect.  It builds interdependency models from this
analysis and uses them to find errors and propose fixes.  
(<a
href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/papers/kim-gil-ijcai01.pdf">Kim and Gil, IJCAI-01</a>)

<p />
<n /> builds upon previous work on <a
href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/">EXPECT</a> using Interdependency Models (<a
href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/link/publications.html#Kim-Gil-AAAI-99">Kim and Gil
AAAI-99</a>, <a
href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/link/publications.html#Kim-Gil-AAAI-2000">Kim and Gil
AAAI-2000</a>).  The work on EXPECT analyzed problem-solving interdependencies,
which model how different pieces of problem solving (procedural) knowledge
relate to each other and to the class definitions in domain ontologies.  Our
initial work concentrates on <i>process models</i>, i.e., knowledge
describing activities and subprocesses as well as their relationships.

<p />
<n />'s checks are done on the simulated execution of the process
model.  Using skolem instances, we can check general scenarios of the
animation of a process. The result of each animation are used as a model of
interdependencies among the sub-steps of the process model.  <n /> performs a
variety of verification checks to process models, including <i>unachieved
conditions of steps</i> in a process model, <i>expected and unexpected
effects, potential loops</i>, and <i>disjunctive model branches</i>.  <n />
will also help users with validation checks of <i> redundancies</i>, and
<i>resource use</i> within a process model.

  <img src="images/kanal-architecture.gif"/>
	 

<p />
KANAL has been used by various end users including biologists who built and
tested models of complex molecular biology processes and army officers who
used KANAL to critique their plans, i.e., courses of action (COAs). We
found that its analysis report was very useful for checking the plans that
were entered by users and often suggested useful ways of improving the
plans. However we also found that sometimes users wish to extend the
background knowledge that is used to produce the analysis report. For
example, they may want to define various special cases of actions that are
relevant for different situations, or exceptions that were not specifically
addressed in the general background knowledge. In general, knowledge bases are
never complete and it is important to provide a capability of adapting the
knowledge base for varying needs. To support this capability we have extended
our authoring environment so that the user can choose to enter special cases
of critiquing knowledge as well as to change the description of the process
itself in order to improve the resulting report. In this extension,
instead of describing different cases in a single definition, we make use of
the inheritance mechanism in the given knowledge representation system to
represent each special case as a separate entity.  We believe that this
approach provides a more a natural view of special cases for end users and has
efficiency advantages.
The details are described in <a 
href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/papers/kim-blythe-iui-2003.pdf">Kim and
blythe, IUI-2003</a>.

<p /> 

    </long>
  </description>

  <research>
    <short>
     Process Models, Verification and Validation, Knowledge Acquisition
    </short>
    <long>
<n /> checks process models specified by a user reports possible errors in
the models, and generates specific suggestions to the user about how to fix
those errors.  Our approach is inspired on previous work on <a
href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/">EXPECT</a> using Interdependency Models (<a
href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/papers/kim-gil-aaai99.pdf">Kim and Gil
AAAI-99</a>, <a
href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/papers/kim-gil-aaai-2000.pdf">Kim and Gil
AAAI-2000</a>).  KANAL analyzes the interdependencies among the individual
steps of a process model.  For example, a simulation of the execution of the
steps allows KANAL to anlayze interdependencies between the conditions and
effects of different steps, such as that the required conditions for each step
are met when the step is supposed to take place, and that the expected effects
of the overall process are in fact obtained.

<p /> The kinds of checks performed and the kinds of fixes proposed by <n /> include

<ul>
<li> Unachieved Preconditions
</li>
<li> Unachieved Expected Effects
</li>
<li> Unordered Steps
</li>
<li> Inappropriate Execution of Steps
</li>
<li> Inappropriate Loops
</li>
<li> Inappropriate Disjunctive Branches
</li>
<li> Inappropriate Branches
</li>

</ul>

The KANAL has been used by
various end users including biologists who built and tested models of complex
molecular biology processes and army officers who used KANAL to critique their
plans, i.e., courses of action (COAs). We found that its analysis report was
very useful for checking the plans that were entered by users and often
suggested useful ways of improving the plans. However we also found that
sometimes users wish to extend the background knowledge that is used to
produce the analysis report. For example, they may want to define various
special cases of actions that are relevant for different situations, or
exceptions that were not specifically addressed in the general background
knowledge. In general, knowledge bases are never complete and it is important
to provide a capability of adapting the knowledge base for varying needs. To
support this capability we have extended our authoring environment so that the
user can choose to enter special cases of critiquing knowledge as well as to
change the description of the process itself in order to improve the resulting
report. In this extension, instead of describing different cases in a single
definition, we make use of the inheritance mechanism in the given knowledge
representation system to represent each special case as a separate entity. We
believe that this approach provides a more a natural view of special cases
for end users and has efficiency advantages. The details are described in 
<a 
href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/papers/kim-blythe-iui-2003.pdf">Kim and
blythe, IUI-2003</a>.


    </long>

  </research>

<link>
<b> KANAL design and implementation</b>
  <ul>
  <li>
   <a href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/projects/KANAL/api.txt">KANAL API</a> </li>
  <li>
   <a href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/projects/KANAL/releases.html">KANAL Implementation on KM</a></li>
  </ul>

<p /> 
<b> KANAL slides in various meetings </b>
  <ul>
  <li><a
href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/kanal/slides/kanal-ae-pi-nov-02.ppt">PI meeting
(Nov 02)</a></li> 
  <li><a
href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/kanal/slides/kanal-10-01.ppt">PI meeting
(Oct 02)</a></li>
 <li><a
href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/kanal/slides/kanal-feb-02-pi.ppt">PI meeting
(Feb 02)</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/projects/KANAL/slides/KANAL-SRI-meeting-10-00.ppt">SRI RKF meeting (10/11/00)</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/projects/KANAL/slides/KANAL-jan-01-rkf.ppt">RKF PI meeting (Jan/01)</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/projects/KANAL/slides/test-k-intro-in-training.ppt">Test Knowledge (intro)
(April)</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/projects/KANAL/slides/Virus-Invades-Cell-trial-in-shaken.ppt"> design of the KANAL
interface (a) (Mar/01)</a></li> 
  <li><a href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/projects/KANAL/slides/Virus-Invades-Cell-in-shaken.ppt"> design of the KANAL
interface (b) (Mar/01)</a></li>
  </ul>
</link>

 
  <link>

<p /> 
  <b>Related Project Links</b>
  <ul>

  <li><a href="http://www.ai.sri.com/~rkf/">SHAKEN homepage</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.iet.com/Projects/RKF/">IET RKF page</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/mfkb/RKF/">University of Texas
RKF participation</a></li>
  </ul>
  </link>


 

<!-- Demo -->
<demo>
<p />
<video width="1000" height="800" controls>
  <source src="kanal-demo-video.m4v" />
Your browser does not support the video tag.
</video>
<div style="font-size:11px;text-decoration:underline">Kanal demo video</div>

<center>
<b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="+1">A Screen Walkthrough
Demonstration of <n /></font></b>
<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica">KANAL November 2002</font></b></center>

<br />
<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="-1">Start with the SHAKEN Login
Screen. KANAL is currently used
within an end-to-end KA system called SHAKEN. </font></b>
<p /><img src="demoimages/shaken-login.gif" />
<br />
<br />
<br />

<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="-1">
You can start KANAL by
selecting "Test Knowledge" from the SHAKEN main window. </font></b>
<p /><img src="demoimages/shaken-main-window.gif" />
<br />
<br />
<br />


<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="-1">You can select or search for
the name of the process model you want to test.</font></b>
<p /><img src="demoimages/kanal-test-knowledge-main.gif" />
<br />
<br />
<br />


<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="-1"> Before you run KANAL, you can
specify the effects you intend to achieve from the process model.
You can either check if intermediate steps achieve intended effects or the
overall plan (process model) achieve the effects using these. </font></b>
<p /><img src="demoimages/kanal-expected-effects.gif" />
<br />
<br />
<br />

<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="-1"> This window shows the KANAL
results. The summary section at the top lists the steps where KANAL found
some errors (or warnings). By clicking each step listed on the left, you can
see the detailed results from KANAL. This destroy step seems fine.
You can see that an expected effect (remaining strength of unit 4 being
greater than 0.7) was not achieved.</font></b>
<p /><img src="demoimages/kanal-first-run.gif" />
<p /><img src="demoimages/kanal-step-info.gif" />
<br />
<br />
<br />

<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="-1"> KANAL found a failed
precondition: the available force ratio is not greater than or equal to 5.
The "force ratio explanation" provides the details.</font></b>
<p /><img src="demoimages/kanal-first-run-warnings-found.gif" />
<br />
<br />
<br />

<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="-1"> KANAL provide several general
suggestions for this problem.  (In other cases, KANAL can produce
more specific suggestions on how to fix the error).  In this case user choose to create
a special case of the Destroy-Unit to address the given situation. </font></b>
<p /><img src="demoimages/kanal-suggestions-window.gif" />
<br />
<br />
<br />

<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="-1"> KANAL provide several general
suggestions for this problem.  (In other cases, KANAL can produce
more specific suggestions on how to fix the error).  In this case user choose to create
a special case of the Destroy-Unit (called Destroy-Unit-Mechanized-Infantry)
to address the given situation. </font></b> 
<p /><img src="demoimages/kanal-creating-special-case.gif" />
<br />
<br />
<br />

<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="-1"> User makes agent being
Mechanized-Infantry-Brigade as the trigger (defining criteria) of the new
action definition. This special case of Destroy-Unit will be used when its
agent is a Mechanized-Infantry-Brigade </font></b>  
<p /><img src="demoimages/action-editor-convert-to-trigger.gif" />
<br />
<br />
<br />

<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="-1"> In this case the
Required-Force-Ratio-Value is 2 instead of 5.</font></b> 
<p /><img src="demoimages/action-editor-final.gif" />
<br />
<br />
<br />

<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="-1"> User tests the same
plan with the new definition (Destroy-Unit-Mechanized-Infantry)
and the warning is now gone.</font></b> 
<p /><img src="demoimages/kanal-second-run-warning-gone.gif" />
<br />
<br />
<br />

<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="-1"> Summary of state transition:
KANAL generates a table for each property that chanages over time in order to
visualize changes made objects in a plan.</font></b> 
<p /><img src="demoimages/kanal-time-varying-properties.gif" />
<br />
<br />
<br />


<P>

</P>



   
</demo>
</project>
