<!-- <?xml version='1.0'?> -->

<!--

IF YOU CAN READ THIS, YOUR BROWSER DOESN'T SUPPORT XML.

PLEASE UPDATE YOUR BROWSER, OR VIEW THE HTML VERSION OF THIS PAGE.

-->
<!--
When the schema works, reference it like this; change the project tag below to this
<project xmlns:xsi = "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation = "isd-personnel.xsd">
-->
<project>
  <name>dialog-manager</name>
  <title>Dialogue Management for Knowledge Acquisition</title>

  <status>
    <short>
   We just started to work on the initial spec.
  </short>
  <long>

</long>
 
  </status>

  <description>
    <short>
     We are trying to build a Dialog Manager that can
keep track of the user's actions and can make suggestions for how to proceed
in building knowledge base.
    </short>

    <long>

<p />
We are developing a dialogue manager that uses KA plans to keep 
track of the user's actions and can make suggestions for how to 
proceed.  The dialogue manager would support: 1) generation, to 
suggest to the user what to do next based on the library of KA plans, 
2) recognition, to track what the user is doing in terms of the KA 
plans.  The dialogue state would be shown to the user as a "status" 
window, where the user could see the currently active KA plans as a 
list of bullets and sub-bullets, each bullet would be checked if 
completed and collapsed when all its sub-bullets are completed.  The 
user could choose to toggle between a "suggest" mode (generation) and 
a "comment" mode (recognition).  We could also keep a history of the 
user's sessions, and be more forceful to impose the "suggest" mode to 
new users or when a more experience user tries a new 
feature/capability of the system.

<p />
A new capability that we'd like to support with this work is 
meta-level interaction with the user.  By allowing users to 
manipulate/edit the status window, they could indicate whether a 
certain task is completed (e.g., I'm done adding sub-steps).

<p />
To develop the library of KA plans we would draw ideas from 
Intelligent Tutoring Systems, in effect trying to make SHAKEN a 
smarter student.  An initial (old) outline is posted at 
 <a href="http://www.isi.edu/~gil/rkf/ITS.ppt">
http://www.isi.edu/~gil/rkf/ITS.ppt</a>.  For example, ITS often start by 
showing the student the purpose of a lesson, partly to give the 
student a roadmap but also to detect any gaps in the student's prior 
knowledge assumed by the lesson.  There are many other interesting 
points about controlling nested subdialogues, teaching strategies, 
providing immediate feedback, etc.

<p />
An intriguing possibility is to use this as a way to 
determine/compare the quality of human tutors by looking at how and 
how much they complete the KA plans (how organized their lessons are, 
how thorough with details), and eventually to train human tutors 
through practicing with the system.

<p />
We have done some previous work in this area on KA Scripts and 
PSMTool, several papers are available at 
<a href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/link/papers-ka.html">
http://www.isi.edu/expect/link/papers-ka.html</a>.
<p />

More details are available at 
<a href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/projects/rkf/dialog-manager.html">
http://www.isi.edu/expect/projects/rkf/dialog-manager.html</a>.
<p />
    </long>
  </description>

  <research>
    <short>
     Dialog Management, Dialog Strategies, Mixed-Initiative systems, Agenda
    </short>
    <long>
    Please see our <a
href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/projects/rkf/dialog-manager.html">initial
sketch</a> of the dialog manager.
    </long>
  </research>

  <link>
   <a href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/projects/rkf/dialog-manager.html">Initial Sketch</a>
  </link>
  <link>
   <a href="http://www.isi.edu/~gil/rkf/ITS.ppt">
   Drawing ideas from Tutoral Dialogs</a>
  <ul>
  <li><a
href="http://www.pitt.edu/~circle/Projects.html">CIRCLE project</a> 
  </li>

  <li>CIRCSIM
  </li>
  <li>Why project 
  </li>
 <li> ...</li>
  </ul>
  </link>

  <link>
  Dialog Systems
  <ul>
   <li><a
href="http://www.cs.rochester.edu/research/cisd/projects/">Trips/Trains</a> 
  </li>
   <li><a
href="http://www.merl.com/projects/collagen/">Collagen</a> 
  </li>
  <li> ...</li>
  </ul>
  </link>

  <link>
  Our previous work in this area
  <ul>
  <li><a
href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/web/ka-scripts/">KA
script</a></li>

  <li><a
href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/web/psmtool/">
PSM Tool</a></li>
  </ul>
  </link>



<!-- Demo -->
<demo>
<P>

</P>



     <center>
	  <img src="../tn_comingsoon.jpg"/>
	  </center>


</demo>
</project>
