<!-- <?xml version='1.0'?> -->

<!--

IF YOU CAN READ THIS, YOUR BROWSER DOESN'T SUPPORT XML.

PLEASE UPDATE YOUR BROWSER, OR VIEW THE HTML VERSION OF THIS PAGE.

-->
<!--
When the schema works, reference it like this; change the project tag below to this
<project xmlns:xsi = "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation = "isd-personnel.xsd">
-->
<project>
  <name>SCEC/IT</name>
  <title>Information Infrastructure for Earthquake Research</title>

  <status>
    <short>
      This project started in September 2001.


    </short>

    <long>
      <p>

 <u>Objective</u>: We are developing intelligent reasoners and interfaces that
enable users to 1) publish implemented codes of earthquake simulation models
and describe model constraints 2) access published simulation models and check
constraint violations, and 3) interactively construct computational
pathways. We are developing a novel approach to interactive pathway
composition that uses knowledge bases to represent and reason about model
constraints and planning approaches to reason about the relationships among
components within an end-to-end pathway computation.  We are also
investigating how to model the grid execution environment so that the user can
be isolated from the details of the execution of the pathway.  
<p>
<u>Systems
Developed</u>: <ul>

<li><A href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/cat">CAT</A> (Composition
Analysis Tool): CAT facilitates interactive construction of computational
pathways where users select and connect existing SCEC components, and the
system generates assistance in completing a correctly formulated
pathway. Given a sketch of a pathway, CAT analyzes it using the semantic
description of components, reports errors and gaps, and generates specific
suggestions on how to fix these errors. When a pathway is completed, it forms
an end-to-end simulation for earthquake scientists.  


<li><A href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/docker">DOCKER</A>
(Distributed Operations of Code with
Knowledge-based descriptions for Earthquake Research): DOCKER is a tool that
enables model developers to publish the code for their models, describe I/O
parameter types in terms of SCEC ontologies, and specify and document
constraints of model use. DOCKER helps end users access models from a uniform
interface, invoke models correctly by enforcing constraints, and find
appropriate simulation models for their requirements.

<li>Artemis : We have done some preliminary work in using query planning
techniques to access metadata catalogs in the grid. Artemis isolates the users
from the complexity of using distributed heterogeneous catalogs by providing
interactive assistance to formulate valid, integrated queries using a single
ontology that is automatically mapped to the particular metadata of each
catalog.  

</ul>
<p>
<u>CAT Integration with SCEC/IT infrastructure</u>: In Spring 2004, we
participated in a successful end-to-end demo of CAT integrated with the SCEC
grid workflow execution system.  The following shows a SCEC user interface with the
results of the execution in the SCEC grid environment of a pathway created
with CAT.  The left-hand side is a rendering of the knowledge base that
represents all the components and abstract component types that the user can
include in the pathway.  This is based on our Year 1 work on the DOCKER
system.
<IMG SRC="images/scec-integration.bmp">


<p>

<u>Recent Work</u>: We are developing CAT-S, a service-based architecture
based on CAT that can also be used to check the correctness of a workflow but
that can be invoked programmatically from other applications and user
interface modalities.  Given a specification of a workflow, CAT-S analyzes it
using the semantic descriptions of components, reports errors and gaps, and
generates specific suggestions on how to fix these errors.  CAT-S can be
reinvoked with a selection of suggestions, and will fix the workflow
accordingly.  The interaction can thus proceed stepwise, with each analyze
followed by an apply fix call, until the pathway is completed.  Our plan is to
integrate CAT-S with the Pegasus workflow planning and execution system that
has been recently adopted for SCEC.  <p>
      </p>
    </long>
  </status>

  <description>
    <short>
      This is a multi-site collaboration to 
provide information technology infrastructure for earthquake research, 
including knowledge representation and reasoning, Grid technologies,
digital libraries, and interactive knowledge acquisition.
    <p><center><img src="scec.png"></center>
     <b>Figure : </b>
The SCEC/IT project, funded by the National Science Foundation (NSF), is developing a new framework for physics-based simulations for seismic hazard analysis building on several information technology areas, including knowledge representation and reasoning, knowledge acquisition, grid computing, and digital libraries.   The project is a collaboration between ISI and other members of the Southern California Earthquake Center (www.scec.org) headquartered at the USC campus, including the US Geological Survey, the San Diego Super Computing Center, Carnegie Mellon University, and UC Santa Barbara

    </short>

    <long>
<p>
Recent advances in geophysics have made it possible for the first time
to create fully three-dimensional simulations of fault-rupture and
fault-system dynamics.   Such physics-based simulations are crucial to
gaining a fundamental understanding of 
earthquake phenomena, and they
can potentially provide enormous practical benefits for assessing and
mitigating earthquake risks through improvements in seismic hazard
analysis.  This project
represents a collaboration among the 
<a href="http://www.scec.org">
Southern California Earthquake Center (SCEC)</a>, the 
<a href="http://www.isi.edu">
Information Sciences Institute (ISI)</a>, the 
<a href="http://www.iris.edu">
San Diego Supercomputer Center (SDSC)</a>, the
<a href="http://www.iris.edu">
Incorporated Institutions for Seismology (IRIS)</a>, 
and the 
<a href="http://www.usgs.gov">
U.S. Geological
Survey (USGS)</a>.
</p>

More on: 
<a href="http://www.scec.org/outreach/eqbasics/eqabc.html">earthquakes</a>
<a href="http://www.iris.washington.edu/seismic/60_2040_1_4.html">earthquake map</a>, 
<a href="http://www.scec.org/research/master.html">shaking frequency map</a>, 
<a href="http://www.scec.org/phase3/images/amplification.jpg">shaking amplification map</a>.

<p>
To achieve its objectives, the environment must provide a means for
describing, configuring, instantiating, and executing complex
computational pathways that result from the composition of various
earthquake simulation models.  This entails solving a number of
challenging problems in information technology. Many object types must
be manipulated, and a number of algorithms must be employed.  Algorithm
inputs and outputs can be very complex and take different meanings for
users in different disciplines.  Models are developed in distributed
collaborations, and any model component may require access to remote
databases and data sets, as well as require remote high-performance
computing resources for its execution.  To solve these problems, we will
bring together research from several distinct computer science
disciplines:
</p>

<ul>
<li> <b>Knowledge representation and reasoning</b> techniques to manage the
heterogeneity of the models and capture the complex relationships
between the physical processes and the model algorithms, between the
algorithms and the simulation codes, and between the simulation codes
and the data products.  Knowledge-based inference will be used to apply
these representations to the problems of pathway construction,
constraint checking, execution planning, and information access. </li>

<li> <b>Grid technologies</b> to enable access to distributed simulation codes
and resources for the timely execution of the simulation scenarios
defined by users, specifically by integrating high-performance computing
resources into the execution environment available to the modeling
framework.  By providing mechanisms for the discovery, access, and
management of distributed computation and storage resources, Grids
address the distributed nature of the developers, resources and user
environments. </li>

<li><b>Digital library</b> technology to manage the collections of data and
simulation code repositories and handle multiple versions of the models.
 Knowledge-based data management tools will provide an infrastructure
for mediating access to existing seismic data catalogs and information
repositories, as well as incorporating new collections of data generated
by the simulations. </li>

<li><b>Interactive knowledge acquisition</b> techniques to enable users with a
range of sophistication to configure computational pathways.  Knowledge
acquisition tools support this activity by selecting appropriate
simulation software and input data files from the available code and
information repositories.  These tools hide implementation details and
present users with structured dialogues that guide them to provide
information required to set up each simulation while resolving the
constraints among the simulation models and their inputs. </li>
</ul>

<p>
The proposed research will be conducted
by a collaboration between leading researchers in each of these
information technology areas and earthquake scientists.
</p>
    </long>
  </description>

  <research>
    <short>
     Interactive knowledge acquisition, semantic markup, composition of software and services.
    </short>
    <long>
<p>
This project is a multi-site collaboration 
to develop an integrated framework for creating, executing, and managing
physics-based earthquake simulations required to predict strong ground
motions.  
Working with members of the 
<a href="http://www.scec.org">
Southern California Earthquake Center (SCEC)</a>,
our goal is to provide effective delivery of simulation products to a
broad-based user community of geophysicists, civil and structural
engineers, city planners, and emergency managers.
</p>

This project will develop new
techniques for describing, configuring and executing complex
computational pathways resulting from the composition of various
simulation components.  In particular, this project brings 
together four distinct computer science disciplines: 
<ul>
<li> knowledge representation and reasoning, by
<a href="http://www.isi.edu/isd/LOOM/">ISI's PowerLoom project</a>,
to manage the heterogeneity of the simulation models
and capture the complex relationships between physical processes,
research simulation models, simulation code, and data products</li>
<li> Grid resource-sharing environments, through
ISI's Center for Grid Computing and 
<a href="http://www.globus.org">Globus</a>,
to support the execution of simulation scenarios in high performance 
computing resources</li>  
<li> digital libraries and information management,
by UCSD, to manage the collections of data and 
simulation code repositories as well as multiple versions of the models</li>
<li> interactive knowledge acquisition, by
<a href="http://www.isi.edu/expect">us</a>,
to enable users with a wide range of sophistication to compose
multi-step simulations from libraries of simulation codes and data</li>
</ul>

The contribution of our research group to this project
is threefold:

<ul>
<li> interactive tools that enable users that are not geophysics experts
to compose and run simulations</li>
<li> distributed representations using semantic markup languages of 
earthquake related information</li>
<li> dynamic planning and execution techniques that will 
enable users to run simulations in the computational Grid</li>
</ul>


<p>
While we will focus on the application of
this new computer science to the challenge problem of seismic hazard
analysis, the techniques and integrated modeling framework that will be
developed in this project will be directly applicable to many other
disciplines.
</p>
    </long>
  </research>

  <mainlink>
   <a href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/docker">Docker</a>
  </mainlink>
  <link>
<a href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/docker">
Interactive knowledge acquisition work: Pathway Assembly Tools</a>
  </link>

  <link>
<a href="http://www.scec.org/cme/">
The official page of the SCEC/IT project</a>
  </link>

  <link>
<a href="http://www.scec.org">
Southern California Earthquake Center (SCEC)</a>
  </link>

  <link>
ISI's Center for Grid Computing and the
<a href="http://www.globus.org">Globus</a> project
  </link>

<!-- Demo -->
<demo>
     <center>
	  <img src="tn_comingsoon.jpg"/>
	  </center>
</demo>
</project>
