<!-- <?xml version='1.0'?> -->

<!--

IF YOU CAN READ THIS, YOUR BROWSER DOESN'T SUPPORT XML.

PLEASE UPDATE YOUR BROWSER, OR VIEW THE HTML VERSION OF THIS PAGE.

-->
<!--
When the schema works, reference it like this; change the project tag below to this
<project xmlns:xsi = "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation = "isd-personnel.xsd">
-->
<project>
  <name>SLICK</name>
  <title>Skills for Learning to Interactively Capture Knowledge</title>
 
  <status>
  <short>
  A prototype KA dialogue is implemeted for  acquiring two very different
types of knowledge: military plans and biological process models.
  </short>
  <long>

<ul>

<li> Acquiring Process Description: A SLICK prototype is built for SHAKEN 
(Clark et al 2002) where the users specify
specify process 
models in terms of their substeps and the objects involved.  Users model a
substep as a type of action from the actions available in the knowledge base
(e.g., `Collide', `Move', etc), and specifies the objects that fill the
required roles for that action (e.g., `agent', `object', `location', etc).
SLICK is built to help users entering  such process models. The slides show the
<a href="slides/slick-for-entering-bio-process-models.ppt">interfaces</a>.
This particular scenario shows how SLICK reports some of the issues in the KB
that went unnoticed by users. SLICK keeps track of the progress based on
learning goals and maintain annotations to the KB accordingly.
The histroy shows the issues resolved and the new issues arisen.</li>

<li> Acquiring Courses of Actions: A SLICK prototype is built to help
military officers enter their plans (courses of actions).
 <a
href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/slick/slides/slick-for-coa-entry-interfaces.ppt"> These slides show
the current interfaces.</a> </li>
</ul>

  </long>
  </status>

  <description>
    <short>
Developing acquisition interfaces that are proactive
learners, able to reason about learning activities and with initiative in
participating in the process accordingly.
    </short>

    <long>
The goal of our work is to develop acquisition interfaces that are proactive
learners, able to reason about learning activities and with initiative in
participating in the process accordingly.  Our approach is to enable
acquisition tools to have acquisition goals and be aware of the level of
competence and confidence of the knowledge they are acquiring.  Drawing from
limitations shown by previous tools in their interactions with users and from
learning/teaching strategies that are typically used in tutoring systems, we
formulated goals and strategies to turn acquisition tools into better
students.  
 <br />
  <img src="images/slick-architecture.gif"/>
	 

    </long>
  </description>

  <research>
    <short>
    Interactive Knowledge Acquisition Dialogue, Deriving Acquisition
Principles from Tutoring Principles
    </short>
    <long>
 <p />
Current tools for interactive knowledge capture have little or no learning
aptitude.  They are mostly oblivious to the process or strategy that the user
may be following in entering new knowledge, unaware of their progress during a
session, and ignorant of typical skills expected from a good student.  A user
has to make up for these shortcomings by tracking the status, progress,
potential problems, and possible courses of action themselves.  We present an
approach to make acquisition interfaces more proactive by extending them with:
1) goals that represent what remains to be learned, 2) strategies to achieve
these goals and acquire further knowledge, and 3) awareness of the current status
of the body of knowledge learned.  The resulting interaction shows that the
system is aware of its progress towards acquiring the new knowledge, and moves
forward by understanding what acquisition goals and strategies to pursue.
<br />
<ul>
<li>Analyzed the
literature on tutorial dialogues and compiled useful principles
that students and teachers typically follow in making tutoring/learning interactions
successful. The result of this work is presented in the <a
href="papers/Tutoring-Learning-Principles-Kim-Gil-02.pdf">ITS-2002 paper (in
proceedings of the Intelligent
Tutoring Systems Conference)</a>
 <br />
<img src="images/learning-and-tutoring-goals.gif"/></li> 

<li>Examined what tutoring and learning principles have been
used to date in the acquisition literature, though unintentionally and
implicitl and how a more thorough and explicit representation of
these principles would help improve enormously how computers learn from users. <a
href="papers/KA-Dialog-Kim-Gil-02.pdf">CogSci-2002 paper (in proceedings of the 24th Annual
Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society)</a>
 <br />
<img src="images/lg-used-in-ka.gif"/>
</li> 

<li> Developed an
approach to make acquisition interfaces more proactive by extending them with:
1) goals that represent what remains to be learned, 2) strategies to achieve
these goals and acquire further knowledge, and 3) awareness of the current
status of the body of knowledge learned.  
A prototype KA dialog system for acquiring military plans is described in <a
href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/slick/slides/slick-pi-nov-02.ppt">slides
</a>
 <br /></li> 


    </ul>
    </long>
  </research>

  
  <link>
  <b>slides in various meetings</b>
  <ul>
  <li><a
href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/slick/slides/slick-pi-nov-02.ppt">PI meeting
(Nov 02)</a></li>
<li><a
href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/slick/slides/Dialog-Feb-02-pi.ppt">PI meeting
(Feb 02)</a></li>

  </ul> 
  </link>

<link>
<a href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/echo"><b>The Echo project for memory-based
meta level reasoning</b></a>
  </link>


<!-- Demo -->
<demo>
<center>
<b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="+1">A Screen Walkthrough
Demonstration of <n /></font></b>
<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica">Version 1.0, November 2002</font></b></center>

<br />
<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="-1">User enters a plan
(courses of action sketch) using nuSketch.
 </font></b>
<p /><img src="demoimages/bh-len.gif" />
<br />
<br />
<br />

<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="-1">When user start entering
a new plan (COA), all the objects are not assigned to any task (shown in red).
The goals and expected effects can provide the purpose of the lesson.
 </font></b>
<p /><img src="demoimages/slick-0.gif" />
<br />
<br />
<br />

<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="-1">Slick shows the task
descriptions being built, issues resolved over time.
 </font></b>
<p /><img src="demoimages/slick1.gif" />
<br />
<br />
<br />

<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="-1">Slick shows the remaining 
tasks and suggestions.  Based on the number of times tested/used by the user,
SLICK computes the confidence level on a given subtopic.
Users can check the details on each objects
introduced during the KA session. 
 </font></b>
<p /><img src="demoimages/slick2.gif" />
<br />
<br />
<br />
<p /><b><font face="Arial,Helvetica" size="-1">Slick maintains history:
changes in the KB. User can check the progress over time.
 </font></b>
<p /><img src="demoimages/slick-history.gif" />
<br />
<br />
<br />

</demo>
</project>
