
<!-- <?xml version='1.0'?> -->

<!--

IF YOU CAN READ THIS, YOUR BROWSER DOESN'T SUPPORT XML.

PLEASE UPDATE YOUR BROWSER, OR VIEW THE HTML VERSION OF THIS PAGE.

-->
<!--
When the schema works, reference it like this; change the project tag below to this
<project xmlns:xsi = "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation = "isd-personnel.xsd">
-->
<project>
  <name>Inspect</name>
  <title>An Air Campaign Planning Evaluation Aid</title>
  <description>
    <short>
    <n/> is an air campaign plan critiquing tool. Current funding is
    supporting thechnology transition to the Joint Defense Planner, which is on
    the path to becoming an integral part of TBMCS. INSPECT was originally
    developed under the DARPA Rome Laboratory Planning Initiative, and was
    demonstrated at the first US Air Force Expeditionary Force Experiment (EFX-98).
    </short>
    <long>
    <n/> is a plan evaluation tool that was built using the EXPECT framework to develop
    knowledge-based systems. <n/> was initially developed as part of the work that the EXPECT
    project is doing under the the DARPA/Rome Laboratory Planning Initiative (ARPI) to create tools
    that support the US military in developing air campaigns. <n/> is now being extended in
    several important dimensions under the DARPA JFACC program. 
    <p/><n/> takes an air campaign plan that has been manually developed and looks for possible
    problems that a user may have overlooked, such as inconsistencies or unrealistic use of
    resources. An important part of the work on <n/> was the development of structured
    representations (or grammars) for air campaign plans. 
    <p/><n/> was an integral part of two important demonstrations: ARPI's Fourth Integrated
    Feasibility Demonstration (IFD-4) in June 1996 and the Jumpstart Demonstration of the DARPA
    JFACC program in January 1997.
    </long>
  </description>
  <research>
    <short>
    Generating explanations and justifications, ISR, strategy and plan rationale.
    </short>
    <long>
    <p/><n/> is being extended in several important dimensions under the DARPA
    JFACC program. Some of these extensions require basic R&amp;D work on the EXPECT
    framework on generating explanations and justifications for <n/>'s
    recommendations, and on Web-based tools to support domain experts to change
    <n/>'s knowledge base. Other extensions will widen the scope of <n/>'s
    evaluations to do the following:
    <ol>
    <li>Include additional types of objectives (such as force
    support (logistics) and force enhancement (ISR - intelligence, Surveillance
    and reconaissance).</li>
    <li>Evaluate the plan from a more global
    perspective that would include information about strategy and plan rationale.</li>
    </ol>
    </long>
  </research>
  <funding>
    <program>DARPA Joint Forces Air Component Commander (JFACC)</program>
    <awardnumber>F30602-97-C-0118</awardnumber>
    <startdate>April 1997</startdate>
    <enddate>September 2000</enddate>
  </funding>
  <link>The <a href='http://arpi.isx.com/'>DARPA/Rome Laboratory Planning Initiative (ARPI)</a></link>
  <link>The <a href='http://yorktown.dc.isx.com/iso/planning/jfacc.html'>DARPA JFACC program</a></link>
</project>
