
<!-- <?xml version='1.0'?> -->

<!--

IF YOU CAN READ THIS, YOUR BROWSER DOESN'T SUPPORT XML.

PLEASE UPDATE YOUR BROWSER, OR VIEW THE HTML VERSION OF THIS PAGE.

-->
<!-- 
When the schema works, reference it like this; change the project tag below to this 
<project xmlns:xsi = "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation = "isd-personnel.xsd">
-->
<project>
  <name>Temple</name>
  <title>Template Enhancement through Knowledge Acquisition</title>
  <description>
    <short>
    Under the <n/> project, we are developing tools to guide users in
    adding planning constraints and preferences, including wizards and
    smart editors.
    </short>
    <long>
    <p />
    The Active Templates program (AcT) is developing a robust,
    lightweight software technology for aiding in the automation of
    detailed planning and execution for military operations and other
    highly-coordinated activities using a plan spreadsheet
    metaphor. Active Templates are distributed data structures whose
    variables can be linked to live data feeds or problem-solving
    methods. Active Templates assist with automated planning and
    execution by capturing, improving and updating critical
    information such as current state, goals, constraints, alternative
    actions, standard defaults, problem-solving context over time,
    decisions, and rationale. Active Templates are designed to be
    user-tailorable, networked, noise-tolerant, user-supported,
    scalable and widely adopted.  
    
    <p />Within AcT, the <n/> project is developing software tools to
    aid a user in adding new constraints to active templates. This
    work makes use of prior work on problem-solving methods and
    script-based acquisition for plan evaluation performed under HPKB
    and ARPI. We have developed the <a
    href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/constable/project-main-view.xml">Constable</a>
    system for examining and modifying constraints used while checking
    a plan, and demonstrated it for planning a SEAL beach infiltration.
    </long>
  </description>
  <research>
    <short>
    <p /> 

    Constraints are used to check that a plan in development is
    feasible. Typically, a plan is checked with many different
    constraints, that check different aspects of the plan and use
    different information.  Users need to be able to modify constraints
    because the particular objectives and rules to follow are often
    unique to the current situation. We are developing Constable, a tool
    that helps users to modify the constraints that they are using to
    check a plan. We provide a uniform interface to different data
    sources that also allows users to integrate these sources within the
    constraints that are applied.

    <p /> 

    This work involves research in the areas of knowledge
    aquisition scripts, dependency analysis, intelligent user
    interfaces and integrating information sources.
    </short>
    <long>
    Constraints allow users of active templates to related different
    pieces of information in checking that a plan is feasible. Users
    need to be able to modify constraints because the particular
    objectives and rules to follow are often unique to the current
    situation. We are developing Constable, a tool that helps users to
    modify the constraints that they are using to check a plan. We
    provide a uniform interface to different data sources that also
    allows users to integrate these sources within the constraints
    that are applied.

    <p /> 

    This work involves research in the areas of knowledge aquisition
    scripts, dependency analysis, intelligent user interfaces and
    integrating information sources.  Under the Temple project we are
    developing the Constable system for managing constraints using KA
    wizards and an English-based constraint editor. Constable provides
    wizards to help a user examine and make modifications to the
    constraints being used to check the plan, and add new
    constraints. For more details, see the individual project pages
    for <a
    href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/constable/project-main-view.xml">Constable</a>
    and <a
    href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/web/english-editor/project-main-view.xml">the
    English editor</a>.
    </long>
  </research>

  <demo>
  Please see the 
  <a href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/constable/demo.html">
  Constable demo</a>.
  </demo>

  <status>
  <short>
  We have developed the <a
  href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/constable/project-main-view.xml">
  Constable</a> system for checking and modifying constraints on plans as
  they are being developed. Constable has been demonstrated in the
  context of planning a SEAL beach landing. We are now integrating
  Constable with Data Agent so that users can view and modify
  constraints over the same live data sources that Data Agent uses.
  </short>
  </status>

  <link><a href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/projects/temple/october-2000.ppt">
  Slides from our presentation at the October 2000 meeting</a></link>

  <link><a href="http://www.isi.edu/info-agents/Heracles">Heracles</a></link>

  <link><a href='http://schafercorp-ballston.com/active-templates'>DARPA Active Templates (AcT) program</a></link>
</project>
