<!-- <?xml version='1.0'?> -->

<!--

IF YOU CAN READ THIS, YOUR BROWSER DOESN'T SUPPORT XML.

PLEASE UPDATE YOUR BROWSER, OR VIEW THE HTML VERSION OF THIS PAGE.

-->
<!--
When the schema works, reference it like this; change the project tag below to this
<project xmlns:xsi = "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation = "isd-personnel.xsd">
-->
<project>
  <name>Planet</name>
  <title>Planet: an ontology for plans</title>


  <description>
    <short>
      Planet is a reusable ontology for representing plans that is
      designed to accomodate a diverse range of real-world plans, both
      manually and automatically created. We have used it for
      modelling, reuse and integration of planning tools, and in a
      variety of domains. It is available in Loom, KIF and CycL.
    </short>

    <long>
      <p /> As we develop larger and more complex intelligent systems
      in knowledge-intensive domains, it becomes impractical to
      develop knowledge bases from scratch. Recent research
      investigates how to develop intelligent systems by drawing from
      libraries of reusable components that include both ontologies
      and problem-solving methods. Planet is a reusable ontology for
      representing plans that is designed to accomodate a diverse
      range of real-world plans, both manually and automatically
      created. We have drawn from our past experience in designing,
      developing and integrating planning tools, and expect planet to
      ease these tasks in the future in three ways. First, we have
      already found it useful for knowledge modelling. By providing a
      structure that formalizes useful distinctions for reasoning
      about states and actions, a knowledge engineer can find the
      semantics of informal expressions of plans (e.g., textual or
      domain-specific) through designing mappings to the
      ontology. Second, a plan ontology can be a central vehicle for
      knowledge reuse across planning applications. Planet contains
      general, domain-independent definitions that are common and
      useful across planning domains. Third, Planet can facilitate
      integration of planning tools through knowledge sharing.

      <p /> Currently, practical efforts to integrate planning tools
      are done by designing separate interchange formats for (almost)
      each pair of tools, since designing a more universal format is
      costly and often more difficult than designing the entire set of
      pairwise formats. These difficulties are in part because these
      systems include decision-support tools such as plan editors,
      plan evaluation tools, and plan critiquers, which represent
      plans in ways that are different from traditional AI plan
      generation systems. Planet can provide a shared plan
      representation for systems to communicate and exhange
      information about the plan, and can facilitate the creation of a
      common, overarching knowledge base for future integrations of
      planning tools.

      <p /> Planet is available in Loom, KIF, and CycL. Send email to
      Jim Blythe (blythe@isi.edu) or Yolanda Gil (gil@isi.edu) if you
      would be interested in seeing the latest version.

    </long>
  </description>

  <research>
    <short>
     In order to provide broad coverage of many different planning
    approaches, we represent a plan in terms of <i>contexts</i>,
    <i>external constraints</i>, for example user advice and
    preferences, and <i>commitments</i> made during the planning
    process.

    <p /> We have used Planet in three quite different planning domains,
    covering both human and machine-generated plans, and
    task-decomposition and goal-subgoal structures.
   </short> 

    <long>

    In order to provide broad coverage of many different planning
    approaches, we represent a plan in terms of <i>contexts</i>, which
    capture planning background information that is independent of a
    particular planning episode, <i>external constraints</i>, for
    example user advice and preferences, and <i>commitments</i> made
    during the planning process.

    <p /> 
    The overview of the PLANET ontology below shows the central concepts
    and relations. Some arrows do not have targets, indicating relations
    whose ranges are not fixed by the ontology.

    <p /> <img src="ont.gif" />
      
    <p />
    We have used Planet to represent plans in three real-world domains
    with very different features:
    <ul>
    <li /> In an air campaign planning domain, where plans are expanded by
    humans an a task-decomposition structure.
    <li /> In a COA analysis domain, where plans are entered by experts
    and tasks have explicitly entered purposes and optionally supporting
    tasks.
    <li /> In a workarounds domain to replace or repair damaged bridges,
    where plans were automatically generated and then evaluated by a
    separate tool.
    </ul>
    </long>
  </research>

  <link>
  </link>

<!-- Demo -->
<demo>

See our <a href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/papers/gil-blythe-aaai00-2.pdf">
AAAI workshop paper</a> for example plans in the ontology.

</demo>

  <status>
    <short>
      Work on Planet began in 1998 under the DARPA HPKB program. It is
      available in Loom, KIF or CycL by email from <a
      href="mailto:blythe@isi.edu">the authors</a>. We would
      appreciate your comments.
    </short>
    <long>
      <p /> We developed Planet as part of our work in the DARPA High
      Performance Knowledge Bases (HPKB) program. Planet is a
      middle-level theory that represents planning knowledge. We
      worked with personnel from Cycorp to integrate Planet into CYC,
      which resulted in an extension to the CYC IKB.

      <p /> We used Planet to develop a system for Course of Action
      (COA) Critiquing for the DARPA HPKB Battlespace Challenge
      Problem.

      <p /> We have demonstrated using Planet in this approach to
      integration in our work on the <a
      href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/rosetta/">Rosetta
      project</a>, an ISO Technology Integration Experiment between
      High Performance Knowledge Bases and Control of Agent-Based
      Systems exploring ontology-based agent communication.

      We also use Planet in our work on a problem-solving method for
      plan evaluation (see <a
      href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/evaluation/">here</a>
      for details).

      <p /> Planet is available in Loom, KIF, and CycL. Send email to
      Jim Blythe (blythe@isi.edu) or Yolanda Gil (gil@isi.edu) if you
      would be interested in seeing the latest version.

    </long>
  </status>


</project>
