<!-- <?xml version='1.0'?> -->

<!--

IF YOU CAN READ THIS, YOUR BROWSER DOESN'T SUPPORT XML.

PLEASE UPDATE YOUR BROWSER, OR VIEW THE HTML VERSION OF THIS PAGE.

-->
<!--
When the schema works, reference it like this; change the project tag below to this
<project xmlns:xsi = "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation = "isd-personnel.xsd">
-->
<project>
  <name>Pegasus</name>
  <title>Planning and execution in grids</title>

  <status>
    <short>
<p>
The AI planner, using <a
    href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/afs/cs.cmu.edu/project/prodigy/Web/prodigy-home.html"
    target="new">
    Prodigy</a>, has been fully integrated with Pegasus for arbitrary
    domains for which an abstract workflow can be provided.
</p>
<p>
Earlier, we used the planner in creating, mapping and executing
    workflows in the LIGO domain.
</p>
    </short>
    <long>
<h2 style="font-size:14px"><a href="http://pegasus.isi.edu">
Pegasus</a> helps scientists find gravitational waves using LIGO data.</h2>
<object CLASSID="clsid:02BF25D5-8C17-4B23-BC80-D3488ABDDC6B" 
WIDTH="530" HEIGHT="530" CODEBASE="http://www.apple.com/qtactivex/qtplugin.cab#version=6,0,2,0">
<param NAME="controller" VALUE="TRUE"/>
<param NAME="type" VALUE="video/mpeg"/>
<param NAME="autoplay" VALUE="false"/>
<param NAME="target" VALUE="myself"/>
<param NAME="src" VALUE="http://www.isi.edu/~deelman/ligo3.mpeg"/>
<param NAME="pluginspage" VALUE="http://www.apple.com/quicktime/download/indext.html"/>
<embed  WIDTH="530" HEIGHT="530" CONTROLLER="TRUE"
SRC="http://www.isi.edu/~deelman/ligo3.mpeg">
</embed>
</object>
<div style="font-size:10px">Searching for Gravitational Waves in Pulsars
and Other Stellar Objects</div>

<p>Gravitational waves, though predicted by Einstein's theory of
relativity, have never been observed experimentally.  Through
simulations of Einstein's equations, scientists predict that those waves
should be produced by colliding black holes or collapsing
supernovae.</p>
<p>The Laser Interferometry Gravitational-Wave Observatory (LIGO)
project aims to detect such phenomena.  At $300M, it is the largest
single enterprise ever undertaking by National Science Foundation.  With
facilities in Livingston, Louisiana and Hanford, Washington, LIGO joined
gravitational-wave observatories in Italy, Germany and Japan in
searching for these signals.  Pulsars are believed to generate such
waves, so scientists search areas with known pulsars as well as other
areas in the hope that they will find other objects that emit them as
well.</p>
<p>The <a href="http://pegasus.isi.edu">Pegasus</a> planner that we have
developed is one of the tools that scientists can use to analyze data
collected by LIGO.  In the Fall of 2002, a 17-day data collection effort
was held, followed by a two-months run in February of 2003 and a
six-month run that will start in late 2003.  LIGO instruments are
designed to measure the effect of gravitational waves on test masses
suspended in a vacuum.  The data collected during experiments is a
collection of time series (multi-channel). The observations are
processed through Fourier transforms and frequency range extraction
software. This may involve composing a workflow of hundreds of jobs and
executing them in appropriate computing resources on the grid, which
gets unmanageable very fast.</p>
<p><a href="http://pegasus.isi.edu">Pegasus</a> was used with LIGO data
collected during the first scientific run of the instrument, which
targeted a set of locations of known pulsars as well as random locations
in the sky.  <a href="http://pegasus.isi.edu">Pegasus</a> generated
end-to-end grid job workflows that were run over computing and storage
resources at Caltech, University of Southern California, University of
Wisconsin Milwaukee, University of Florida, and NCSA.</p>
<p>The screenshot and movie above show a visualization of the results of
a pulsar search.  The search ranges are specified by scientists on the
lower left corner of the screen.  The top left corner shows the specific
range displayed in this visualization.  The bright points represent the
locations searched.  The red points are pulsars within the bounds
specified for the search, the yellow ones are pulsars outside of those
bounds.  Blue and green points are the random points searched, within
and outside the bounds respectively.</p>

<p><b>Acknowledgements:</b> The LIGO application of <a
    href="http://pegasus.isi.edu">Pegasus</a> was developed at USC/ISI
    by Ewa Deelman, Jim Blythe, Yolanda Gil, and Carl Kesselman in
    collaboration with A. Arbree, R. Cavanaugh, K. Blackburn,
    A. Lazzarini, S. Koranda, G. Mehta, K. Vahi, S. Patil, S. Rao, and
    G. Singh.  The visualization of LIGO data shown here was created by
    M. Thiebaux. The original picture of the sky comes from the 2MASS
    (The Two Micron All Sky Survey--NASA) collection.  For more
    information, please visit the GriPhyn project page, the <a
    href="http://pegasus.isi.edu">Pegasus</a> project page, and the <a
    href="http://www.globus.org">Globus</a> project page.</p> 
</long>
    </status>

  <description>
    <short>
    Pegasus is a flexible framework that enables the mapping of
    complex scientific workflows onto a grid. We are studying AI
    planning and scheduling techniques to support this mapping within
    the overall <a href="http://pegasus.isi.edu" target="new">Pegasus project</a>,
    which is led by 
    <a href="http://www.isi.edu/~deelman" target="new">Ewa Deelman</a>.
    </short>

    <long>
<p>
Our work uses a wide-range of AI technology to improve current Grid
middleware. Within <a href="http://pegasus.isi.edu"
target="new">Pegasus</a> we concentrate on planning techniques to
generate job workflows for execution in a Grid environment and dynamic
planning and scheduling techniques for robust execution of job
workflows, but also touching on ontology-based matchmaking for computing
resources and reasoning about meta-data to automate the composition of
distributed problem-solving components based on the user's desired end
products as part of the <a
href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/cognitive-grids">Cognitive Grids</a>
project.
</p>
    </long>
  </description>

  <research>
    <short>
     AI planning and scheduling applied to grid environments.
    </short>
    <long>
<p>
Cognitive grids are a collaboration
between Grid and AI researchers at ISI aimed to
provide intelligent middleware for Grid computing infrastructure.
Our initial work has been exploratory and driven by the 
<a href="http://www.griphyn.org">
GriPhyN</a>
and the
<a href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/scec-it">
SCEC/IT</a> projects.
</p>

<p>
One of the challenges for scientists is to configure complex workflows
of components and to setup the complex scripts required to execute each
component (e.g., FFT code) as a job on a specific grid resource (e.g., a
linux cluster).  One of the applications within the GriPhyN project is
the Laser Interferometer Gravitational Wave Observatory (LIGO), where
instruments collect data that needs to be analyzed in order to detect
gravitational waves predicted by Einstein's theory of relativity.  One
of the tasks involved is pulsar searches in certain areas of the sky for
a time period, where observations are processed through Fourier
transforms and frequency range extraction software.  This may involve
composing a workflow of hundreds of jobs and executing them in
appropriate computing resources on the grid, which gets unmanageable
very fast. In addition, you have to spend a lot of time to become a
knowledgeable grid user in order to do this, even if you have simple job
workflows to run.  Physicists may be happy to do this (though they would
probably prefer not to), but other potential users of scientific
software may not be.  Last but not least, using the grid is not free and
means sharing resources with others, so intelligent middleware can make
grids more efficient and accessible overall.
</p>

<p>
Our approach to these problems is to use automated planning techniques
combined with knowledge representation and reasoning to specify the
capabilities and requirements of these components as well as the
capabilities offered by computing and storage resources available on the
grid.  We are developing <a href="http://pegasus.isi.edu"> Pegasus</a>
(Planning for Execution in Grids), a configurable system that can
generate and execute complex workflows on the Grid.  Pegasus includes an
AI planner that uses information about the capabilities and requirements
of each domain-specific component (e.g., FFT code or simulation code) in
terms of meta-data requirements and results (e.g., a seismic hazard
simulation takes a fault model as input) as well as resource
requirements.  Pegasus uses the Metadata Catalog Service (MCS), newly
developed at ISI, to perform the mapping between application-specific
attributes and logical file names of existing data products. AI-based
planning technologies are used to construct an end-to-end workflow,
taking into account preferences and other heuristics to minimize
execution time or data movement.  Pegasus also contains a Virtual Data
Language generator that can populate the Chimera catalog with newly
constructed derivations. Finally, Pegasus generates the necessary submit
files and sends the Workflow to the grid's DAGMan for execution.  We
have used Pegasus for LIGO pulsar search, using LDAS and compute and
storage resources at Caltech, University of Southern California,
University of Wisconsin Milwaukee, University of Florida, and NCSA.
This application was demonstrated at the Supercomputing Conference
(SC-2002).
</p>

<p>
Our future plans include incorporating these techniques in the new
service-based grid architecture proposed by OGSA (Open Grid Services
Architecture), dynamic planning and scheduling techniques for robust
execution of job workflows, and using the grid as a robust
infrastructure for distributed heterogeneous agent communities.
Our work on Pegasus forms part of our work on the 
<a href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/cognitive-grids">Cognitive Grids</a>
project, along with work on interactive workflow construction and 
ontologies for resource match-making.
</p>
    </long>
  </research>

<link><a href="http://pegasus.isi.edu">Pegasus</a></link>
<link><a href="http://www.globus.org">Globus</a></link>
<link><a href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/cognitive-grids">Cognitive Grids</a></link>
<link><a href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/scec-it">SCEC/IT</a></link>
<link><a href="http://www.isi.edu/ikcap/docker">DOCKER</a></link>
<link> <a
    href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/afs/cs.cmu.edu/project/prodigy/Web/prodigy-home.html">
    Prodigy</a></link>

<!-- Demo -->
<demo>
<h2 style="font-size:14px"><a href="http://pegasus.isi.edu">
Pegasus</a> helps scientists find gravitational waves using LIGO data.</h2>

<object CLASSID="clsid:02BF25D5-8C17-4B23-BC80-D3488ABDDC6B" 
WIDTH="530" HEIGHT="530" CODEBASE="http://www.apple.com/qtactivex/qtplugin.cab#version=6,0,2,0">
<param NAME="controller" VALUE="TRUE"/>
<param NAME="type" VALUE="video/mpeg"/>
<param NAME="autoplay" VALUE="false"/>
<param NAME="target" VALUE="myself"/>
<param NAME="src" VALUE="http://www.isi.edu/~deelman/ligo3.mpeg"/>
<param NAME="pluginspage" VALUE="http://www.apple.com/quicktime/download/indext.html"/>
<embed  WIDTH="530" HEIGHT="530" CONTROLLER="TRUE"
SRC="http://www.isi.edu/~deelman/ligo3.mpeg">
</embed>
</object>
<div style="font-size:10px">Searching for Gravitational Waves in Pulsars
and Other Stellar Objects</div>
</demo>
</project>
