<!-- <?xml version='1.0'?> -->

<!--

IF YOU CAN READ THIS, YOUR BROWSER DOESN'T SUPPORT XML.

PLEASE UPDATE YOUR BROWSER, OR VIEW THE HTML VERSION OF THIS PAGE.

-->
<!--
When the schema works, reference it like this; change the project tag below to this
<project xmlns:xsi = "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation = "isd-personnel.xsd">
-->
<project>
  <name>MathTrust</name>
  <title>Mathematical Analysis of Trust and Deception</title>

  <status>
    <short>
  This project started in November of 2005.
    </short>

    <long>
  This project started in November of 2005.
    </long>
  </status>

  <description>
    <short>
MathTrust is a formal, quantitative analysis of trust, which can be
applied to determine trust in information sources.
    </short>

    <long>
Information systems such as the Web often include open information
sources that have very varying quality, and may be subject to deception.
The information is often of unknown origins and there is often no prior
history with many of the sources that may be used to assess their
reputation. 

This project will investigate how to represent, learn, and characterize
the reputation and reliability of sources in an information system that
collects from users their individual trust ratings and derives over time
their collective consensus trust. This project will analyze the factors
that affect trust in sources, study how to capture user feedback, and
develop algorithms to derive source reputation. Based on this model of
trust, a mathematical analysis of source trust and deception will relate
formally a number of salient factors that influence trust in information
systems.

    </long>
  </description>

  <research>
    <short>
Trust, Semantic Web, Algorithms
    </short>
    <long>
    The main research thrusts of this work are:
	<ul>
	<li>representing trust in information sources</li>
	<li>capturing trust in information sources from users</li>
	<li>learning and computing trust in information sources</li>
	</ul>
    </long>
  </research>

<!-- Demo -->
<demo>
     <center>
	  <img src="tn_comingsoon.jpg"/>
	  </center>


</demo>
</project>
