<!-- <?xml version='1.0'?> -->

<!--

IF YOU CAN READ THIS, YOUR BROWSER DOESN'T SUPPORT XML.

PLEASE UPDATE YOUR BROWSER, OR VIEW THE HTML VERSION OF THIS PAGE.

-->
<!--
When the schema works, reference it like this; change the project tag below to this
<project xmlns:xsi = "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation = "isd-personnel.xsd">
-->
<project>
  <name>Pathway Assembly Tool</name>
  <title>Interactive Knowledge Acquisition: Pathway Assembly Tool</title>

  <status>
    <short>
      This project started in September 2001.
    </short>

    <long>
      <p>
      This project started in September 2001.
      </p>
    </long>
  </status>
  <description>
    <short>
      The Pathway Assembly Tool will enable unsophisticated users to 
      compose complex computational pathways from individual simulation software.
    </short>

    <long>
    <p>
Users who are not programmers or knowledge engineers will use this tool
to setup a computational pathway corresponding to an end-to-end
simulation by (1) selecting simulation models from a library, (2)
setting up the input parameters required, and (3) coordinating
interacting constraints across models in the overall computational
pathway.
</p>
<p>
Our testbed will be the simulation models contributed by participants
of the 
<a href="http://www.isi/edu/expect/web/scec-it">
SCEC-IT</a>
project, an NSF-funded effort to provide information
technology for earthquake research.
</p>
    </long>
  </description>

  <research>
    <short>
     Knowledge Acquisition, Planning, Software composisition.
    </short>
    <long>
    <p>
The Pathway Assembly Tool will enable unsophisticated users to 
      compose complex computational pathways from individual simulation software.
      </p>
<p>
We cast the composition of 
computational pathways as a planning problem.  The user will be
prompted for requirements in terms of the desired intensity measures and
accuracy of the results of the simulation, as well as the computational
resources available.  These will be turned into planning goals and
resources.  Pathway templates will be considered plan decomposition
fragments that the user weaves together and instantiates.  The Pathway
Assembly tool will also include a suite of Pathway Construction
Strategies that capture typical requirements and dataflow interactions
among models within a pathway.  Inputs and outputs of the individual
components and their associated constraints will be expressed as
required preconditions and expected effects.  For example, this will
enable the tool to detect that one of the inputs required by a
ground-motion model is an earthquake forecast model, which can only be
generated by an earthquake forecasting simulation. In contrast with
other planning tools, our system will be able to exploit knowledge-rich
structures that describe tasks and goals. The Pathway Assembly
tool will be developed as a plan-authoring environment, where the tool
is helping the user by checking that the preconditions, effects, goals,
resources are adequately handled.  This planning framework fits
well the paradigm of the Grid execution environment with respect to
handling resources, scheduling, and bringing up the need for replanning
when the authored plan is not feasible.
</p>
<p>
Our work builds on previous research on the EXPECT architecture for
knowledge analysis and interactive acquisition, which has been
used to acquire planning knowledge.  The central thesis of EXPECT is
that if the tool understands how individual pieces of knowledge relate
to each other, then it can understand how new knowledge fits and what
additional knowledge is missing and, as a result, guide users in adding
it.  To this end, EXPECT analyzes a knowledge base and automatically
derives Interdependency Models between problem-solving knowledge
(procedures to achieve goals and tasks), ontologies (object models), and
factual knowledge (data).  Interdependency Models can be used to plan
acquisition dialogues that organize the interaction with users into
meaningful topics and sequences of related questions.  EXPECT has been
used to develop an interactive tool for acquisition of planning
constraints, ranging from simple value preferences and bounds to complex
procedural constraints.  For example, geophysicists can express simple
constraints such as "compute the Coulomb stress change for all faults
parallel to the San Andreas Fault", or more complex constraints such as
"compute the maximum Coulomb stress change seen on all faults with a
strike within 30 degrees of the local strike of the San Andreas fault,
and a dip steeper than 60 degrees, knowing that only through-going
faults breaking the entire seismogenic zone contribute significantly to
the hazard change."  EXPECT has been used for other planning domains
including air-campaign planning, special operations, and logistics. 
EXPECT's approach to knowledge acquisition has been evaluated
successfully in diverse domains with users such as Army officers,
project assistants, and non-CS students.  Building on the ideas in
EXPECT, we recently developed KANAL, a prototype tool for checking the
correctness of manually developed process models and plans by exploiting
Interdependency Models.
</p>
<p>
The main research problems addressed by this tool are: 
<ul>
<li>how to
enable users who are not experts in programming or knowledge engineering
to formulate computational pathways that are ready for the execution
environment</li>
<li>how to hide from users the details of the models of the
software components and their constraints, while enabling them to
understand enough to decide which alternative simulation models to use
and how</li>
<li>how to design plan-authoring tools that take into account
scheduling, execution failures, and replanning issues brought up by the
high performance computing execution environment in the Grid.</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p>
Although many issues related to software modeling, reuse, and
configuration may arise during this work, the tool that we are building
is highly focused on earthquake applications.  Similarly
focused research projects for configuring software have been successful
for applications such as image processing, engineering design, and
planning interplanetary science missions.  We believe that using
knowledge-rich community models for earthquake science
will enable us to develop more
sophisticated and capable environments that will make the
pathway-assembly process accessible to end-users.
</p>
    </long>
  </research>

  <link>
The <a href="http://www.isi/edu/expect/web/scec-it">
SCEC-IT</a> project
  </link>

  <link>
<a href="http://www.scec.org/scec2/index.html">
The official page of the SCEC/IT project</a>
  </link>

  <link>
<a href="http://www.scec.org">
Southern California Earthquake Center (SCEC)</a>
  </link>

  <link>
ISI's Center for Grid Computing and the
<a href="http://www.globus.org">Globus</a> project
  </link>

<!-- Demo -->
<demo>
     <center>
	  <img src="tn_comingsoon.jpg"/>
	  </center>
</demo>
</project>
