<!-- <?xml version='1.0'?> -->

<!--

IF YOU CAN READ THIS, YOUR BROWSER DOESN'T SUPPORT XML.

PLEASE UPDATE YOUR BROWSER, OR VIEW THE HTML VERSION OF THIS PAGE.

-->
<!--
When the schema works, reference it like this; change the project tag below to this
<project xmlns:xsi = "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation = "isd-personnel.xsd">
-->
<project>
  <name>JIGSAW</name>
  <title>Helping People Connect Software</title>

  <status>
    <short>
  This project started in September of 2001.
    </short>

    <long>
  This project started in September of 2001.
    </long>
  </status>

  <description>
    <short>
      Intelligent interface to enable unsophisticated users to 
      configure and compose software systems and web sites through
      semantic markup.
    </short>

    <long>
	We are developing intelligent interfaces and tools that enable 
	naive users to:
	<ul>
	<li> find relevant software systems and Web sites for their purposes</li>
	<li> create customized access to the software</li>
	<li> invoke software systems and Web sites and store their results</li>
	<li> compose software systems together to create more complex computations and results</li>
	</ul>
	
	This work is being used in two different contexts.  We are using this system
	as a 
	<a href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/web/path-assembly/">
	Pathway Assembly Tool</a>
	to compose complex simulations for earthquake research.
	We are also using this system to assemble agents to 
	do complex tasks as part of the 
	<a href="http://www.isi.edu/e-elves/">
	Electric-Elves</a>
	project.
    </long>
  </description>

  <research>
    <short>
     Semantic markup, planning, knowledge acquisition.
    </short>
    <long>
    The main research thrusts of this work are:
	<ul>
	<li> <b>Helping users create adequate markup labels</b>:  Many 
	labels used in markup languages such as XML are not 
	meaningful to end users, only to system developers.  
	In order to manipulate the inputs and results of a system,
	this tool would enable users to refer to the information the system 
	uses and produces in a way that is meaningful to them.</li>
	<li> <b>Helping users formulate input constraints</b>:
	Many descriptions of software and Web sites 
	using markup languages such as XML are missing
	details in terms of the constraints that need to be taken
	into account when invoking that system.  
	This tool
	helps users create more precise descriptions of the
	systems they are using, for example by showing them
	randomly generated examples of markup data
	so they can detect and formulate constraints that are missing 
	from the original description.
	</li>
	<li> <b>helping users describe a system in terms of the 
	tasks it performs</b> </li>
	<li> <b>Helping users formulate correct compositions of 
	individual systems</b></li>
	</ul>
    </long>
  </research>

  <link>
	<a href="http://www.isi.edu/expect/web/path-assembly/">
	Pathway Assembly Tool</a>
  </link>
  <link>
	<a href="http://www.isi.edu/e-elves/">
	Electric-Elves</a>
  </link>

<!-- Demo -->
<demo>
     <center>
	  <img src="tn_comingsoon.jpg"/>
	  </center>


</demo>
</project>
