
------------------------------------
-- replaced 2010-09-15, cf 

  This project started in October 2008 as part of the
  DARPA <a href="http://www.darpa.mil/ipto/programs/bl/bl.asp">Bootstrapped
  Learning program</a>.    





      <h3>Challenges in Learning Procedures from Tutorial Instruction</h3>

      <p>
	Human instruction by telling is naturally plagued with omissions,
	oversights, unintentional inconsistencies and errors. Teachers
	also often make incorrect assumptions about the student's
	background knowledge and learning abilities. Humans can learn
	from such imperfect instructions because 1) they assume that
	such phenomena occur in the instruction and 2) they have
	strategies to work around such imperfections. The electronic
	students that we are developing in the BL program for learning
	from being told have similar assumptions and
	strategies. However, the student's task is easier or harder
	depending on the degree and nature of the imperfections in the
	instruction. Five key factors that influence the difficulty of
	learning are:
	<ol>
	  <li>Situating the instruction by introducing objects </li>
	  <li>Describing steps in adequate detail</li>
	  <li>Specifying relations between steps</li>
	  <li>Complexity of conditionals and iterations</li>
	  <li>Background knowledge available to supplement the
	    instruction</li>
	</ol>
      </p>

      <p>
	The first factor is the situation of instruction through introduction
	of objects. That is, instruction of procedures is often framed
	in the context of a general situation, specified by introducing
	a set of generic objects. For example, a lesson may start off by
	saying "suppose you have a route to follow, and a vehicle that
	cannot negotiate slopes of more than 30 degrees", which
	introduces two objects and their types plus a property
	constraint. If the instruction introduces all the objects and
	constraint that will be used in the lesson, it is easier for the
	student to understand how the objects are used throughout the
	procedure. If the instruction does not introduce some of the
	objects, then the student has to hypothesize what the objects
	are and what their types and constraints might be in the
	situations where the procedure must be applied. The more objects
	that are not properly introduced by the teacher, the harder the
	learning task because there are more hypotheses to explore. A
	different dimension that makes learning harder is the resolution
	of references when objects are similar.If there are several
	objects of similar types that are not specifically introduced by
	the teacher, it will be harder for the student to figure out
	which object references might be the same and which might refer
	to a distinct object and therefore figure out how many distinct
	objects need to be present. In those cases, the student has to
	hypothesize and explore more alternative assignments or
	permutations of the data objects.
      </p>

      <p>
	In introducing new objects, another source of difficulty for
	learning is mixing the introduction of the objects within other
	expressions. A case of this is the need to introduce existential
	or universal quantification. For example, in the instruction
	"Suppose there is a company unit c1. If c1 has a mine plow, and
	then do X.", c1 is an input argument for the function being
	learned.However, in general, there can be multiple different
	interpretations of the same expression, depending on the nature
	of the introduced objects and how they are related. For example,
	with this instruction, "Suppose there are a Company unit c1 and
	a Platoon p1. If c1 has p1 and p1 has a mine plow, then do X.",
	if the student knows that multiple platoons are organized into a
	company, the instruction can be also interpreted as "Given a
	company c1, if all the platoons p1 in c1 have a mine plow, then
	do X", or "Given a company c1, if there exists a platoon p1 in
	c1 that has a mine plow, then do X." If such quantification is
	not explicitly stated, the student needs to form multiple
	different hypotheses. The number of hypotheses will grow when
	the student has to consider alternative interpretations of
	multiple objects.
      </p>

      <p>
	The second key factor that makes learning more difficult is the lack
	of necessary details in describing a procedure's substeps. For
	example, the instruction may call a subprocedure as one of the
	steps but omit arguments that are required by the definition of
	the subprocedure.In that case, the student must hypothesize what
	objects may be used to invoked the subprocedure, perhaps also
	hypothesizing objects that were not introduced in the
	instruction. The more arguments missing and the more candidate
	objects, the larger the hypothesis space to explore. Steps can
	also be specified indirectly by mentioning the effect of an
	action but not the action itself. For example, the instruction
	may say "Before starting the engine make sure there is gas in
	the tank." In those cases, the student must rely on prior
	knowledge about actions that may have the effect mentioned, then
	insert the action where it may be appropriate in the
	procedure. The more candidate actions and insertion locations,
	the harder learning is. Instruction may also lack information
	about what to do when exceptions arise. Similarly, else
	statements may not be specified. In these cases, the student is
	unlikely to infer what the missing information is and would have
	to wait for other lessons to learn that (e.g. follow on
	practice).
      </p>

      <p>
	The third key factor is how the relations among steps are
	specified. This includes ordering relations, causal relations,
	dataflow relations, resource relations, and temporal
	relations. In particular, instruction is always provided in a
	sequential order but a procedure's step structure may be quite
	complex and non‐linear. Of immediate concern are step ordering
	relations. The instruction may specify steps in a convenient but
	not necessarily correct order. In addition, steps are given in a
	sequence when the actual dependencies among steps are better
	represented as a partial order. If the step ordering is not
	fully specified or incorrect, the student needs to reason about
	possible steps and step orderings, as well as other
	relationships among them such as causal or dataflow
	relations. The space to explore can grow quickly as the number
	of hypotheses or the degree of ambiguity is higher.
      </p>

      <p>
	An important relationship among steps is based on how the results and
	effects of each step are used by others. Some actions have
	side-effects and do not return any specific result, while other
	actions return an object that can be used as an argument of
	subsequent steps.
	The former typically correspond to representations of physical
	procedures while the latter are functions that are meant to be
	evaluated to find a value. If the student knows that it is
	learning a function, then it can reason about what each step is
	returning and the compatibility between the objects produced and
	returned by each substep as well as the entire function. If the
	student does not know whether it is learning a function or a
	procedure, then it must reason about the effects of each action
	(including side-effects and conditional effects) and the
	prerequisites of other actions in order to figure out how the
	substeps are related.
      </p>

      <p>
	The fourth key factor is the complexity of conditionals and
	iterations. These control constructs are notoriously challenging
	for human teachers to specify in all the detail necessary in
	order for a procedure to be executable. That is, natural human
	instruction typically leaves out important things such as
	initialization and termination conditions for iterations,
	clauses in conditions, and the need to create temporary
	variables (e.g., counters) for iterations. When conditions and
	iterations are present, the student's analysis of the procedure
	becomes more complex. For conditional branches, the student
	needs to consider the alternative data flows and control flows
	possible. For iterations, the student may need to analyze
	several folds in order to understand how a loop needs to
	work. Iterations that are easier to learn involve processing
	sets of objects one at a time. Harder iterations to learn are
	those that require the student to set up loops with new
	variables and infer exceptional initial and termination
	conditions. Conditionals that are easier to learn involve
	checking the state for a new object or property value to
	manifest. More complex conditionals can mention disjuncts and
	negations whose scope may be hard to determine from the
	instruction.
      </p>

      <p>
	Combinations and nestings of conditionals and iterations within a
	procedure make learning harder. When conditional statements are
	nested, instructions typically do not specify the scoping of
	each statement. When scoping is ambiguous, the student must
	create and explore alternative hypotheses. The more
	combinations, the larger the search space that the student must
	explore. Iterations can also be nested, raising the complexity
	of learning because of potential interactions between the
	objects in the inner and outer loops.
      </p>

      <p>
	The fifth key factor that influences the difficulty of learning is the
	availability of adequate background knowledge to help the
	student supplement what is stated in the instruction. The
	student must rely on background knowledge to detect and find
	workarounds to omissions and errors in the instruction. For
	example, if the knowledge base has overgeneral argument types
	for a function, it can lead to overly general hypotheses for an
	object type when the object is used for invoking the
	function. This makes the space of hypotheses larger and harder
	to explore. Also, the system may not be able to detect wrong use
	of an object as an argument of a procedure or function. For
	example, when the argument type is defined as a Number instead
	of a Speed, when a Distance object is assigned to the argument
	the student will not be able to detect the inconsistency. Given
	a set of arguments with overgeneral types (e.g. several Number
	arguments), and a set of objects to be assigned to the
	arguments, alternative assignment combinations would need be
	considered.
      </p>

      <p>
	It is easier to learn when all concepts, vocabulary, and substeps have
	been previously defined for the student (in a prior lesson or as
	background knowledge). It is harder to learn if new vocabulary
	such as a new type of object is introduced in the middle of
	describing how a step is performed, since the student may have
	to backtrack to reason about earlier steps differently given the
	new assumptions introduced by the new object. It is also easier
	to learn a procedure if the substeps have been taught
	previously, since the student can reason about their nature and
	their effects to rule out implausible hypotheses rather than
	having to treat them as a black box of unknown nature that does
	not help the student constrain the space of possible models of
	the procedure being learned.
      </p>

      <p>
	Finally, the difficulty of learning increases in lessons where larger
	numbers of omissions and errors are present. To learn from the
	lesson alone, the student must consider many combinations of
	hypotheses that lead to alternative models of the procedure. The
	student must also be equipped to reason about the plausibility
	and likelihood of models by reasoning over larger amounts of
	background knowledge. In practice, telling is combined with
	other learning methods. A lesson by telling may be followed by a
	demonstration or examples. Alternatively, the student could test
	the alternative models learned from telling, by exercising them
	in a simulation and measuring failures or by getting feedback
	from the teacher on practice problems.
      </p>

      <h3>Approach</h3>
      <p>
	Our approach is to equip our student with an extensive catalog of
	strategies and heuristics that human students use to learn from
	natural and imperfect tutorial instruction. For example,
	teachers do not always introduce all the objects that will be
	referenced in the instruction. When an object is introduced, the
	student would turn it into an input to the procedure. But when
	an object is referenced but not introduced, the student can
	adopt a strategy of making the object be one of the inputs to
	the procedure.
      </p>

      <p>
	The student then applies these strategies and heuristics to 1)
	extract, 2) infer, and 3) hypothesize procedure models from the
	stated instruction. Because learning may never be completed and
	yet the learned procedure may be in good enough shape to be
	used, the student applies these strategies to conduct
	self-assessments of the quality of the learned procedure
	models. Through this process the student develops increasingly
	more refined (detailed) models of the procedure that are
	consistent with the instruction. The student also needs to
	reason about model constraints in order to detect whether a
	model is inconsistent and therefore discard it from further consideration.
      </p>

      <p>
	In parallel to these strategies, we are also investigating the
	possibiliy of combining instructions with explicit
	demonstrations of the procedure being taught, using
	examples. Instruction and demonstration seem to have
	complementary advantages. In particular with respect to the
	first and second challenge above, demonstrations can help. Due
	to their concrete nature, many details become apparant. The
	actions being executed in a demonstration build a ground-truth
	for the specific case on which the example operates. This can
	help disambiguate or fill in omitted details such as missing
	action arguments, ambiguous references, missing scopes for
	program blocks (e.g., the body of a loop), or ambiguous action
	argument mappings. It can also help in disambiguating what was
	meant, when a user uses unknown terms to refer to known
	objects or actions (e.g., using synonyms).	
      </p>

